vpl.ca 2019-12-28

# Protection of Privacy Policy | Vancouver Public Library

For the purposes of this policy the following definitions from the Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act are used:

" **contact information** " means information to enable an individual at a place of business to be contacted and includes the name, position name or title, business telephone number, business address, business email or business fax number of the individual;

" **personal information** " means recorded information about an identifiable individual other than contact information;

" **service provider** ” means a person retained under a contract to provide services for a public body;

" **third party** ," in relation to a request for access to a record or for correction of personal information, means any person, group of persons or organization other than:

(a) the person who made the request, or

(b) a public body.

###  **1 Purposes for Which Personal Information May be Collected**

VPL only collects personal information as permitted by FIPPA. The primary purposes for which VPL collects personal information is for the proper administration of library services and programs and the planning and evaluating of services and programs or purposes consistent with this. Such purposes include, but are not limited to, providing access to library materials, services and programs, room rentals, communications, collection of fines, fees and debts, fundraising, protection of VPL property, security of users and staff, and non-identifying statistical purposes.

###  **2 Collection and Use**

VPL collects and uses personal information in accordance with FIPPA to conduct library business, to provide library services and programs and to evaluate, plan and enhance services and programs.

Personal information will only be collected in accordance with FIPPA. Accordingly, except in the limited circumstances provided for in FIPPA, personal information about an individual will be collected directly from that individual. Individuals are informed of the reasons for collecting personal information at the time (or before) it is collected. In addition, at the time of collection (or before), individuals are informed of VPL’s legal authority for collecting the information and the name, title, and contact information for VPL’s Privacy Officer, responsible for ensuring compliance with FIPPA, to whom questions about the collection can be directed.

Unless an individual consents to some other use, personal information will only be used for the stated purpose for which it is collected. Personal information may be collected for uses such as: access to library materials, services, and programs; room rentals; communications; collection of fines, fees, and debts; fundraising; protection of VPL property; security of users and staff; non-identifying statistical purposes; and in the limited circumstances provided for in FIPPA.

VPL will take reasonable steps to ensure that the personal information held by it is accurate, complete, and up-to-date. VPL will correct an individual’s personal information if it learns from the individual that the information is incorrect.

###  **3 Protection of Personal Information**

VPL uses reasonable security measures to protect against risks such as unauthorized access, collection, use, disclosure, or disposal of personal information. Measures include administrative, physical, technological, and operational safeguards that are appropriate to the nature and format of personal information.

VPL will not retain any personal information longer than necessary for the provision, evaluation, and planning of library services and programs, unless a longer period is required by law.

###  **4 Access**

Members of the public have access to their own personal information. Access to recorded personal information about a member of the public is provided to that individual upon verification of identity.

Individuals with complaints or questions about personal information can contact VPL’s Privacy Officer. (see contact information at end of policy)

###  **5 Disclosure**

VPL will not rent or sell personal information. VPL will not disclose personal information to third parties except in accordance with the exceptions permitted under FIPPA including as set out below or with an individual’s consent. Individuals with complaints or questions about personal information can contact VPL’s Privacy Officer. (see contact information at end of policy)

 **5.1 Minors**

Minors have the same rights as adults with respect to their personal information. A parent or guardian may act for a minor in relation to specified sections of FIPPA.

 **5.2** **Service Providers to the Library**

VPL ensures that any service providers requiring access to personal information to deliver services on behalf of VPL treat personal information in compliance with FIPPA.

VPL will use personal information only for the purpose for which it was obtained or compiled, or for a use consistent with that purpose. VPL will not disclose personal information about individuals without their consent. Providing some library digital products and services may require that VPL shares personal information with a service provider and/or that an individual shares personal information to create a separate account with the service provider. When VPL offers digital products or services that require the user to share personal information or to create an account, VPL will implement a consent process.

VPL may disclose personal information to a collection agency or credit bureau for the purpose of collecting a debt.

 **5.3 Vancouver Public Library Foundation and Friends of the Vancouver Public Library**

Provided an individual has consented to the disclosure, personal information may be disclosed to the Vancouver Public Library Foundation or Friends of the Vancouver Public Library for fundraising purposes.

 **5.4 Police/Law Enforcement**

Personal information may be disclosed to comply with a subpoena, a warrant, or an order by a court, person, or body in Canada with the jurisdiction to compel the production of information, or to respond to a specific written request from a law enforcement agency to assist in a specific investigation, or as required by law.

 **5.5 Emergency Situations**

VPL may disclose personal information under compassionate circumstances; for example, so that next of kin or a friend of an individual who is injured, ill, or deceased can be contacted.

###  **6 Retention**

VPL will not retain any personal information longer than necessary for the provision and planning of library services and programs, unless a longer period is required by law.

VPL may, however, retain personal information related to library services and programs when users opt in to allow the library to do so; for example, to enhance or personalize library services and programs.

VPL’s Protection of Privacy Policy details the purposes for which your personal information may be collected by the library, how it is collected and used, how it is protected, how to access your personal information that has been collected as well as to whom it may be disclosed in accordance with the B.C. Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act (FIPPA).

To be transparent and accountable, the library must publish a Personal Information Bank (PIB) directory of ways we collect, use and share your personal information.

Each listing explains why we collect that information, how we use it, and who we share it with.

Download the PIB directory
